<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Planning and Prep Vault]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>lib\media\favicon.png</url><title>Planning and Prep Vault</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 15:18:16 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="lib\rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 15:18:05 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[Bible Seminar 1 - The church is God's new creation (Acts 2:1-41)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Theme: As Jesus promised, the gathered people of God receive the Holy Spirit and begin to call people from every nation to receive forgiveness and the Spirit as they have. The new covenant creation begins here and starts on its mission to fill the whole earth!<br>Aim: See the privilege of being gathered to God's Spirit-filled new covenant community. Listen and have confidence that forgiveness and the gift of the Spirit is available for you and your friends through repentance and faith in Jesus.<br><br><br>The disciples have obeyed Jesus' command to gather in Jerusalem and wait for the gift of the Spirit that will enable them to fulfil the mission he has given them (1:8). Although there are around 120 gathered (1:15), Luke has drawn our attention to the fact that the number of apostles is back up to 12 (1:26), and that it's now Pentecost. This festival is also called the Feast of Weeks in the OT -- it's a harvest festival, 50 days after Passover, and so it has a sense of completion, joy, and fulfilment -- and that's what we get here. In Jewish thought it had also begun to be associated with the giving of the Law at Mount Sinai (which happened 2 months after the first Passover, Exod 19:1, so roughly the same time difference). And if you know what happened at Mount Sinai, it all sounds very familiar! The anointed leader goes up to God (Moses/Jesus), the divine presence (a great noise and fire, Exod 19:16-19) comes down on 12 tribes/people, there is a gift of God which marks a new beginning for his people (the Law/the Spirit), and a sermon is preached which calls for obedience. After the Passover and the Exodus came the old covenant; after Jesus' cross and resurrection comes the new covenant!<br>But there are both similarities and differences between the two experiences. The crowd outside is not a united people, but a scattered people who are re-gathered from every nation. This is the fulfilment of prophecies such as Isaiah 66:18-23 and Jeremiah 31:10-34 - the ingathering of the exiled people of Israel to Jerusalem to be his people once again. But the people's reaction to the new covenant is perhaps not ideal. Some are interested and amazed, but others are mocking (2:12-13) -- just like the crowds were when Jesus spoke to them, and a foretaste of the response the church will get when they preach the gospel from now on.<br>But there's a good difference too! Previously, Moses was the only Spirit-filled mediator between God and man, and he wished that everyone in Israel could enjoy God's presence in the same way he did (Numbers 11:27-29). Now everyone does! God's fiery presence by his Spirit rests on "all of them" (2:4) without destroying them -- God has come to live with his people once and for all! And as Peter explains with his quote from Joel 2, this is what God always intended (2:14-21). <br>OT Context
Joel 2 is worth looking at closely - in it Joel:

<br>prophesies the judgement of the Lord on his sinful people, via the nations coming like locusts to take the people into exile (Joel 2:1-11);
<br>calls for the right response - that the people should gather together and repent (Joel 2:12-17);
<br>says that the judgement will be turned away and a permanent blessing poured out, but only after a great cataclysm which will be like the end of the world (Joel 2:18-27 -- see Luke 23:44-45);
<br>then prophesies that the Spirit will be poured out on every member of God's people -- not just the prophets, priests, and kings but men and women, boys and girls, masters and servants -- and that when that happens salvation will be available to everyone (Joel 2:14-21).

<br><br>After explaining what's going on, Peter takes the gathered crowd back to the event which has made this new covenant possible -- the death, resurrection, and ascension of Jesus Christ, the new and final Passover sacrifice. <br>The work of the Spirit
It's notable that when the Spirit comes on the people, the first thing that happens is that they all begin to speak God's word and that the theme of their speech is the gospel of Jesus. This is what the Spirit always does -- he shines a spotlight on Jesus with clear, intelligible words, and helps people to respond with repentance and faith (see John 16:7-11, Eph 6:17, 1 Cor 14:19). And the "tongues" here are clearly normal human languages -- Pentecost seems to reverse the curse of Babel by allowing people from every nation to once again gather to understand the word of God!
So don't get bogged down in this session with the apparent "weirdness" of the Spirit's manifestation -- as we can see from the OT context, the Spirit comes to reveal God's plans and make things clearer, not make things more complicated! This is also clearly a spectacular, one-off Sinai-ish experience, not something we should expect to see repeated. There are a few "mini-Pentecosts" in the book of Acts for different groups of people corresponding to the programme of Acts 1:8 (Samaritans in Acts 8, Gentiles in Acts 10, the remainder of the faithful remnant of Israel in Acts 19), but most people are converted and receive the Spirit without anything visibly or audibly spectacular! The 14-18s will get a chance to explore this more thoroughly in the following session.
<br>Peter proves this to the people with the help of three witness:<br>
<br>Their own experience (2:22-24). This is the same crowd who have seen and heard Jesus' "miracles, wonders and signs" (note the Exodus language, Exodus 7:3) which were God's proof of who he was. But instead of accepting him, they colluded with the Gentiles to put him to death -- yet this was all part of God's plan for Jesus to be the true Passover Lamb (2:23). Given Jesus' status as God's chosen king, and sinless perfection which meant he did not deserve to die, it was "impossible for death to keep its hold on him" -- and the people who've been in Jerusalem for the whole time know all this.
<br>David's prophecy (2:25-32). Peter recalls Psalm 16, where King David commits himself to follow God no matter what, and is confident that he will receive an unshakeable and eternal inheritance - his body will never see decay. But Peter rather ironically points his finger to David's grave (2:29)! So how can David say this? It's because David is a prophet (2:30) -- the true singer of this Psalm is David's greater Son Jesus, and Jesus' resurrection is the proof that Jesus is the true Messiah of Israel.
<br>God's vindication (2:33-36). From Jesus' death and resurrection, Peter moves on to Jesus' ascension, which the apostles witnessed less than a fortnight ago (2:32-33, see 1:9). Another prophetic quote from King David explains the point - having been apparently crushed by his enemies, Jesus is now risen and ruling over every nation and will do so until every enemy is destroyed (2:34-35; see Psalm 110:1, which Jesus himself drew attention to in Luke 20:41-44). 
<br><br>The people respond as Joel says they should -- with the conviction that only the Spirit can bring (2:37, c.f. 1 Thess 1:5). They know they are sinners who have mistreated Jesus and they now fear God's righteous judgement. But wonderfully, there is mercy available for them -- they too can repent, trust in Jesus, be baptised, and receive the same Holy Spirit (2:38)! But it's not just for them - as the OT prophesied, it's for both Jews and "far off" Gentiles (2:39), and so the message must go out to "the ends of the earth" (1:8). <br>One final fulfilment of Sinai remains. When Moses came down from the mountain, he found the people worshipping a golden calf -- and the Law which he held in his hands, written on stone, couldn't save or change them (c.f. 2 Cor 3:5-9). In judgement God put to death 3000 people (Exod 32:28). But now Jesus has poured out his Spirit, bringing conviction of sin and turning away from idols -- and his death, resurrection and ascension makes it possible for all to be forgiven and the exiles gathered in. And the result? 3000 people are brought to life (2:41).<br><br><br><a data-href="Main Talk 1 - The church is Jesus' mission (Acts 1.1-11)" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-1-the-church-is-jesus'-mission-(acts-1.1-11).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 1 - The church is Jesus' mission (Acts 1.1-11)</a><br><br><a data-href="Dig Deeper Seminar 1 - The Spirit-filled church" href="\unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminar-1-the-spirit-filled-church.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dig Deeper Seminar 1 - The Spirit-filled church</a><br><a data-href="Main Talk 2 - The church is for Jesus' enemies (Acts 3.11-26)" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-2-the-church-is-for-jesus'-enemies-(acts-3.11-26).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 2 - The church is for Jesus' enemies (Acts 3.11-26)</a>]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-1-the-church-is-god's-new-covenant-creation-(acts-2.1-41).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Bible Seminars/Bible Seminar 1 - The church is God's new covenant creation (Acts 2.1-41).md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 15:15:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite 2024 Bible Seminar 2 - The church is preaching and prayerful (Acts 4:1-31)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Theme: Christ continues to build his church through the bold proclamation of his gospel in spite of opposition.<br>Aim: Boldly speak the gospel even when opposition comes and pray for God’s help in doing this.<br><br>If we are following Jesus the chances are that we will know that speaking for Christ makes life harder. Speaking for Christ may bring awkwardness, opposition, hostility, ridicule and stress. These may even be&nbsp; the reasons stopping us from becoming Christian. Nevertheless, from it’s very first days the church has grown through speaking boldly about Jesus.<br><br>Peter has healed a man ‘in Jesus’ name' (Acts 3:1-9), this presented him with the opportunity to preach (Acts 3:11-26). Peter’s confronts Jesus’ (unwitting) murders with their need to repent (3:19,26). In verses 1-4 we see two different reactions to this, the first is annoyance and vexation (4:2). The priests, the captain of the temple guard (High priests right hand man) and Sadducees (largest group of ruling Jews) object to the message that Peter is preaching. Peter’s message has gone beyond saying that Jesus was resurrected into saying that through him others will be resurrected. The Sadducees naturally oppose this because they didn’t believe there was a resurrection. The others were probably more worried that Peter would cause a disturbance that would cause the Romans to clamp down on Jerusalem further or would upset their position of authority with the people. However, Luke wants us to know that speaking boldly has been effective, the second response is that 5000 men believed the word, presumably more including women. This is why the Jewish leaders act so strongly.<br>Potential application: What do we think will make our friends Christians? Speaking the gospel might not look impressive but is God’s way of growing his church.<br><br>It is ominous that the rulers, elders, scribes and High Priest, the Sanhedrin, gather together in Jerusalem, this is what the kings of the earth do in verse 26. Caiaphas was the High Priest presiding over Jesus’ arrest and execution. Peter had cowered outside Jesus’ trial and denied Christ, however at his own trial the Holy Spirit helps him of speak boldly about Christ (4:8,13). The charge is essentially, ‘who gave you authority to do this?’ (4:7), Peter’s answer is Jesus. Jesus work of salvation is ongoing as this mans healing has shown, in verse 9 the word for healing is actually saved. Salvation and resurrection and healing are all of one piece, the lame man leaping has been given as a small foretaste of resurrection life, the messianic age has arrived (Isaiah 35:6).&nbsp;<br>Psalm 118 foreshadowed what the Jewish leaders had done. In Psalm 118 the king has been rejected by the people of God and thrown out of the city but is vindicated by God and so returns in triumph to be recognised ruler of God’s kingdom, this is precisely what had happened to Jesus. Jesus’ message is wonderfully inclusive, it’s for absolutely everyone, even his enemies, but also very exclusive, salvation can be found nowhere else because no one else has died for your sins. There are no other paths to God.<br>Potential application: What else do people look to to save them? Will anything else work? Getting top grades in exams will not save you because they do nothing to your sins.<br><br>The Sanhedrin were the powerful ruling council of Jerusalem and yet come across as a bit of a joke. Their charge in 4:7 reveals their ignorance, arrogance and fear. They put Peter &amp; John on trial for an act of kindness,&nbsp; (4:9 cf. Luke 6:9-11 doing good). Even uneducated men seem to know more about God than they do (4:13) and more willing to listen to Him (4:19). It is important to notice that they have basically no arguments against the gospel. This would be the perfect opportunity to point out how wrong Peter is about the resurrection but they can neither disprove what has happened nor its significance. Their only option is to try to intimidate Peter &amp; John into silence, which they can’t because their authority is trumped by God (4:19). To crown it all the rulers live in fear of the people they are supposed to lead (4:21) .<br>Further to this, in verse 25-28 the point is that those who oppose God are on the wrong side of history. In Psalm 2:4-6 God laughs at those who oppose him as he establishes his king (Jesus) in Zion. He is not threatened by opposition, it would be a hilarious joke were it not that he takes it very seriously and ‘rebuke them in his anger&nbsp;and terrifies them in his wrath’ (Psalm 2:5). Opposition only succeeds in furthering God’s plans as is demonstrated at the cross. (4:28)<br>Potential application: When it comes to the choice of listening to God or to people who do you listen to and why? It should be no contest but rarely is.<br><br>Peter and John are released and return to their friends. Prayer is the churches instinctive response as they hear what has happened. Firstly their prayer acknowledges who God is; he is the one who spoke heaven and earth into being and the one who is never caught off guard by opposition but powerful works it for his own good purposes. It is not wrong to pray for opposition to end but I suspect that the church didn’t think that was the priority, God’s kingdom even can grow because of opposition. Instead the church prays for bold speech in the face of opposition, a prayer this is answered immediately (4:31). Things shaking are generally a sign of God’s presence. God’s people already have the Spirit but in this particular instance He helps them to speak boldly.<br>Potential application: How do we respond to opposition? Is our response prayerful and faithful that God has it under control? Do we pray for opposition to stop or for more boldness to speak?<br><br><br><a data-href="Main Talk 2 - The church is for Jesus' enemies (Acts 3.11-26)" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-2-the-church-is-for-jesus'-enemies-(acts-3.11-26).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 2 - The church is for Jesus' enemies (Acts 3.11-26)</a><br><br><a data-href="Dig Deeper Seminar 2 - The radically-different church" href="\unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminar-2-the-radically-different-church.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dig Deeper Seminar 2 - The radically-different church</a><br><a data-href="Main Talk 3 - The church is holy (Acts 4.32-5.11)" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-3-the-church-is-holy-(acts-4.32-5.11).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 3 - The church is holy (Acts 4.32-5.11)</a>]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-2-the-church-is-preaching-and-prayerful-(acts-4.1-31).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Bible Seminars/Bible Seminar 2 - The church is preaching and prayerful (Acts 4.1-31).md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 15:15:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite 2024 Dig Deeper Seminar 1 - The Spirit-filled church]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>
<br>Trace the promise of the Spirit in the OT (c.f. <a data-href="MTS Holy Spirit Complete" href="\moorlands\staff-and-mts\holy-spirit\mts-holy-spirit-complete.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">MTS Holy Spirit Complete</a>)
<br>Tackle some big misunderstandings about the Holy Spirit (e.g. he's an "it", he's just about the miraculous/spectacular stuff, he's all about "the gifts")
<br>Think about the democratisation of the presence/power of God in the church
<br><br><a data-href="Bible Seminar 1 - The church is God's new covenant creation (Acts 2.1-41)" href="\unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-1-the-church-is-god's-new-covenant-creation-(acts-2.1-41).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Bible Seminar 1 - The church is God's new covenant creation (Acts 2.1-41)</a><br><br><a data-href="Main Talk 2 - The church is for Jesus' enemies (Acts 3.11-26)" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-2-the-church-is-for-jesus'-enemies-(acts-3.11-26).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 2 - The church is for Jesus' enemies (Acts 3.11-26)</a>]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminar-1-the-spirit-filled-church.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Dig Deeper Seminars/Dig Deeper Seminar 1 - The Spirit-filled church.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 13:57:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite 2024 Evening Talk 1 - The church is Jesus' mission (Acts 1:1-11)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>Now that Jesus has completed his earthly mission, his heavenly mission begins through the church - and we get to both hear and speak the message of his coming kingdom.<br><br><a data-href="Bible Seminar 1 - The church is God's new covenant creation (Acts 2.1-41)" href="\unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-1-the-church-is-god's-new-covenant-creation-(acts-2.1-41).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Bible Seminar 1 - The church is God's new covenant creation (Acts 2.1-41)</a><br><br>This is the opening talk of the camp and as such needs to get us excited about studying Acts together this week! The big theme of this opening passage is that these are not (as traditionally understood) the Acts of the Apostles, but the Acts of King Jesus - if Luke's first volume was all about what Jesus "began to do and to teach" (1:1), then the sequel continues the story. Jesus is still the main actor, even though he will be physically absent from 1:9 onwards. And here he sets the trajectory not only of the book of Acts, but of the rest of human history. If Luke 24:46 describes Jesus' earthly ministry, 24:47 describes his heavenly ministry - repentance and the forgiveness of sins must be preached to all nations in order to complete Jesus' work and usher in the new creation. That's the programme the disciples are commissioned to undertake in Acts. The Day of the Lord has come as they realise in 1:6, but it extends to all nations and to the end of time (1:8) - and with the assurance of their risen King now ascended and ruling from heaven (1:9 - c.f. Daniel 7) and the promise of the Holy Spirit to empower them (1:8), now is not the time to stand around looking for Jesus (1:10-11)! He will return - there is no need to doubt that - and so they must crack on with the mission he has given them. The gospel they proclaimed has, wonderfully, reached us 3000 miles away and 2000 years later; and we too have the privilege of playing our part in the Jesus' mission to build his church.]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-1-the-church-is-jesus'-mission-(acts-1.1-11).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Main talks/Main Talk 1 - The church is Jesus' mission (Acts 1.1-11).md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 13:57:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite 2024 Main Talk 2 - The church is for Jesus' enemies (Acts 3:11-26)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>The wonderful new creation church we saw this morning is not for the "good people" - the promise extends even to those who were complicit in killing Jesus. The right response is to turn and experience God's forgiveness and rest.<br><br><a data-href="Bible Seminar 1 - The church is God's new covenant creation (Acts 2.1-41)" href="\unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-1-the-church-is-god's-new-covenant-creation-(acts-2.1-41).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Bible Seminar 1 - The church is God's new covenant creation (Acts 2.1-41)</a><br><a data-href="Dig Deeper Seminar 1 - The Spirit-filled church" href="\unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminar-1-the-spirit-filled-church.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dig Deeper Seminar 1 - The Spirit-filled church</a><br><br><a data-href="Bible Seminar 2 - The church is preaching and prayerful (Acts 4.1-31)" href="\unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-2-the-church-is-preaching-and-prayerful-(acts-4.1-31).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Bible Seminar 2 - The church is preaching and prayerful (Acts 4.1-31)</a>]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-2-the-church-is-for-jesus'-enemies-(acts-3.11-26).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Main talks/Main Talk 2 - The church is for Jesus' enemies (Acts 3.11-26).md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 13:57:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Acts 1:1–11]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>Τὸν μὲν πρῶτον λόγον ἐποιησάμην περὶ πάντων, ὦ Θεόφιλε, ὧν ἤρξατο ὁ Ἰησοῦς ποιεῖν τε καὶ διδάσκειν<br><br>ἄχρι ἧς ἡμέρας ἐντειλάμενος τοῖς ἀποστόλοις διὰ πνεύματος ἁγίου οὓς ἐξελέξατο ἀνελήμφθη· <br><br>οἷς καὶ παρέστησεν ἑαυτὸν ζῶντα μετὰ τὸ παθεῖν αὐτὸν ἐν πολλοῖς τεκμηρίοις, διʼ ἡμερῶν τεσσεράκοντα ὀπτανόμενος αὐτοῖς καὶ λέγων τὰ περὶ τῆς βασιλείας τοῦ θεοῦ· <br><br>καὶ συναλιζόμενος παρήγγειλεν αὐτοῖς ἀπὸ Ἱεροσολύμων μὴ χωρίζεσθαι, ἀλλὰ περιμένειν τὴν ἐπαγγελίαν τοῦ πατρὸς ἣν ἠκούσατέ μου· <br><br>ὅτι Ἰωάννης μὲν ἐβάπτισεν ὕδατι, ὑμεῖς δὲ ἐν πνεύματι βαπτισθήσεσθε ἁγίῳ οὐ μετὰ πολλὰς ταύτας ἡμέρας. <br><br>Οἱ μὲν οὖν συνελθόντες ἠρώτων αὐτὸν λέγοντες· Κύριε, εἰ ἐν τῷ χρόνῳ τούτῳ ἀποκαθιστάνεις τὴν βασιλείαν τῷ Ἰσραήλ; <br><br>εἶπεν δὲ πρὸς αὐτούς· Οὐχ ὑμῶν ἐστιν γνῶναι χρόνους ἢ καιροὺς οὓς ὁ πατὴρ ἔθετο ἐν τῇ ἰδίᾳ ἐξουσίᾳ, <br><br>ἀλλὰ λήμψεσθε δύναμιν ἐπελθόντος τοῦ ἁγίου πνεύματος ἐφʼ ὑμᾶς, καὶ ἔσεσθέ μου μάρτυρες ἔν τε Ἰερουσαλὴμ καὶ ἐν πάσῃ τῇ Ἰουδαίᾳ καὶ Σαμαρείᾳ καὶ ἕως ἐσχάτου τῆς γῆς. <br><br>καὶ ταῦτα εἰπὼν βλεπόντων αὐτῶν ἐπήρθη καὶ νεφέλη ὑπέλαβεν αὐτὸν ἀπὸ τῶν ὀφθαλμῶν αὐτῶν. <br><br>καὶ ὡς ἀτενίζοντες ἦσαν εἰς τὸν οὐρανὸν πορευομένου αὐτοῦ, καὶ ἰδοὺ ἄνδρες δύο παρειστήκεισαν αὐτοῖς ἐν ἐσθήσεσι λευκαῖς, <br><br>οἳ καὶ εἶπαν· Ἄνδρες Γαλιλαῖοι, τί ἑστήκατε βλέποντες εἰς τὸν οὐρανόν; οὗτος ὁ Ἰησοῦς ὁ ἀναλημφθεὶς ἀφʼ ὑμῶν εἰς τὸν οὐρανὸν οὕτως ἐλεύσεται ὃν τρόπον ἐθεάσασθε αὐτὸν πορευόμενον εἰς τὸν οὐρανόν.]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\text-work\acts-1.1-11.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Text work/Acts 1.1-11.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 10:13:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite 2024 Teaching Timetable - Acts 1-9]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>The goal of this year's Unite is to help the young people appreciate the privilege of belonging to local churches, Jesus' Spirit-filled communities which are both the fulfilment of all God's purposes and the means he is using to reach the nations for his kingdom. <br><br><br>
<br>Decide about world mission day/Q&amp;A? ✅ 2024-02-20
<br>Just me, Joel, Becky evening talks ✅ 2024-02-20
<br>New member for teaching team - Simon, Craig, Tom, Lauren?, Dylan? ✅ 2024-02-20
<br><br>Teaching Team: Joel, Nathan, Tom, Craig
Evening Talks Team: Joel, Nathan, Becky
Seminar Team 11-14: Becky G, Craig, Steve S?, Becky
Seminar Team 14-18: Dan, Nathan, Victoria, Hannah, Neil?, Steve S?<br><br>The idea of this is that we get all the young people together, sitting in their dorm groups, and dramatically (though not over-dramatically!) read through the chunk of Acts we'll be looking at today. Then they have 15 minutes or so simply to react to what they've heard in groups with some simple questions to guide the discussion. It's less of a Bible study than a chance to hear God's word read well and get excited for the day's teaching.<br><br>C.f. <a data-href="Bible Seminars - Overview" href="\unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminars-overview.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Bible Seminars - Overview</a><br>These are done in separate age groups but looking at the same passage. The 14-18s can go into more depth, but the leaders of the two age streams ought to work together to make sure the same points are getting across.  More of a "guided Bible study" than a seminar, with light prep to be done by dorm leaders.<br><br>C.f. <a data-href="Dig Deeper Seminars - Overview" href="\unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminars-overview.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dig Deeper Seminars - Overview</a><br>This is for 14-18s only - I envisage these seminars looking more at the OT background of what's going on in the section we're looking at each day and drawing out the implications.<br><br>These are fairly self-explanatory I think! The morning celebration I haven't given a specific passage for - happy to change this but I think it'd be a good chance to look back over the week and encourage the YP to get involved in the ongoing Acts of King Jesus!<br><br>Instead of the Q&amp;A on Wednesday afternoon, I'd like to invite one or two people involved in world mission to give a presentation about what they're doing - let the YP see both the joy and the hardships of ministry over the world! ]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\unite-2024-teaching-timetable.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Unite 2024 Teaching Timetable.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 13:57:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Untitled]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\untitled.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Untitled.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 16:53:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Untitled 1]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\untitled-1.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Untitled 1.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 16:55:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Untitled 2]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\untitled-2.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Untitled 2.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 16:55:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Untitled 3]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\untitled-3.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Untitled 3.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 16:56:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Untitled 4]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\untitled-4.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Untitled 4.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 16:56:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite 2024 Bible Seminar 3 - The church is organised and prioritised (Acts 6:1-7)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>It's not just from the outside that threats come to Jesus' mission - it's from the inside too! The world invades the church in the form of favouritism; but instead of sorting it themselves, the apostles focus on the main thing - preaching and prayer - and organise servants who can bring godly wisdom to bear on the church's struggles so the word can continue to go out.<br><br><a data-href="Main Talk 3 - The church is holy (Acts 4.32-5.11)" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-3-the-church-is-holy-(acts-4.32-5.11).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 3 - The church is holy (Acts 4.32-5.11)</a><br><br><a data-href="Dig Deeper Seminar 3 - The suffering-speaking church" href="\unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminar-3-the-suffering-speaking-church.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dig Deeper Seminar 3 - The suffering-speaking church</a><br><a data-href="Main Talk 4 - The church is rejected (Acts 7.1-52)" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-4-the-church-is-rejected-(acts-7.1-52).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 4 - The church is rejected (Acts 7.1-52)</a>]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-3-the-church-is-organised-and-prioritised-(acts-6.1-7).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Bible Seminars/Bible Seminar 3 - The church is organised and prioritised (Acts 6.1-7).md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 13:45:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite Bible Seminar 4 - The church is for the nations (Acts 8:4-7, 26-40)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>After the disciples are scattered from Judah, the second stage of Jesus' mission begins - they spread the gospel to both Samaria and even to far-off nations like Ethiopia (home of the Queen of Sheba who was so impressed with Solomon's wisdom)! This is truly an international gospel because Jesus is the suffering Servant who has taken on himself the sins of the whole world.<br>(Thought: do we want to have an international mission focus on this day?)<br><br><a data-href="Main Talk 4 - The church is rejected (Acts 7.1-52)" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-4-the-church-is-rejected-(acts-7.1-52).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 4 - The church is rejected (Acts 7.1-52)</a><br><br><a data-href="Dig Deeper Seminar 4 - The local-global church" href="\unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminar-4-the-local-global-church.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dig Deeper Seminar 4 - The local-global church</a><br><a data-href="Main Talk 5 - The church is for her enemies (Acts 9.1-31)" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-5-the-church-is-for-her-enemies-(acts-9.1-31).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 5 - The church is for her enemies (Acts 9.1-31)</a>]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-4-the-church-is-for-the-nations-(acts-8.26-40).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Bible Seminars/Bible Seminar 4 - The church is for the nations (Acts 8.26-40).md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 14:06:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite 2024 Bible Seminars - Overview]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>The point of these seminars is to get the young people's heads into the Bible for themselves. There's a mixture of upfront input and group work.<br><br>Question - do we start all together with 11-18s? Or split from the beginning?<br>Question - is the upfront bit more of a talk followed by a Bible study (as we're missing this a bit from the Big Read?) Or more of a guided seminar?]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminars-overview.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Bible Seminars/Bible Seminars - Overview.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 10:03:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite 2024 Dig Deeper Seminar 2 - The radically-different church]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>
<br>Trace the theme of holiness throughout the OT - what does it mean to be like God as a community?
<br>See the privilege of being made holy and being different, even if that means standing out 
<br>Preparation for tonight's main talk
<br><br><a data-href="Bible Seminar 2 - The church is preaching and prayerful (Acts 4.1-31)" href="\unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-2-the-church-is-preaching-and-prayerful-(acts-4.1-31).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Bible Seminar 2 - The church is preaching and prayerful (Acts 4.1-31)</a><br><br><a data-href="Main Talk 3 - The church is holy (Acts 4.32-5.11)" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-3-the-church-is-holy-(acts-4.32-5.11).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 3 - The church is holy (Acts 4.32-5.11)</a>]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminar-2-the-radically-different-church.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Dig Deeper Seminars/Dig Deeper Seminar 2 - The radically-different church.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2023 12:57:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite 2024 Dig Deeper Seminar 3 - the suffering-speaking church]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>
<br>Trace the OT theme of the importance/priority of the word of God - see how speaking it always got the prophets in trouble yet God always rewarded them (as prep for the evening talk)
<br>Applications to how local churches prioritise word ministry over other good things that could be done in the world (e.g. social action / social justice); but the church is still a community where its people are cared for (Gal 6:10)
<br>Bring in eschatology - "the church exists to relieve suffering, especially eternal suffering"
<br><br><a data-href="Bible Seminar 3 - The church is organised and prioritised (Acts 6.1-7)" href="\unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-3-the-church-is-organised-and-prioritised-(acts-6.1-7).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Bible Seminar 3 - The church is organised and prioritised (Acts 6.1-7)</a><br><br><a data-href="Main Talk 4 - The church is rejected (Acts 7.1-52)" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-4-the-church-is-rejected-(acts-7.1-52).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 4 - The church is rejected (Acts 7.1-52)</a>]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminar-3-the-suffering-speaking-church.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Dig Deeper Seminars/Dig Deeper Seminar 3 - The suffering-speaking church.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2023 13:04:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite 2024 Dig Deeper Seminar 4 - The local-global church]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>
<br>Look at OT expectations of a nation being chosen as a kingdom of priests to the other nations
<br>See how the theme develops from being about the nations drawn in to the church sent out
<br>Have a world mission focus - hear from Christians/churches around the world?
<br><br><a data-href="Bible Seminar 4 - The church is for the nations (Acts 8.26-40)" href="\unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-4-the-church-is-for-the-nations-(acts-8.26-40).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Bible Seminar 4 - The church is for the nations (Acts 8.26-40)</a><br><br><a data-href="Main Talk 5 - The church is for her enemies (Acts 9.1-31)" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-5-the-church-is-for-her-enemies-(acts-9.1-31).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 5 - The church is for her enemies (Acts 9.1-31)</a>]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminar-4-the-local-global-church.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Dig Deeper Seminars/Dig Deeper Seminar 4 - The local-global church.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2023 12:59:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite 2024 Dig Deeper Seminars - Overview]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>The goal of these seminars is to help the older group dig deeper into the Scriptures with a bit more OT / systematic background to the themes of the earlier Bible Seminars.<br><br>Given that the previous session is a bit more group work, I think this could work better as a traditional seminar - getting them to look at significant sections of the OT and trace the themes to the New.]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminars-overview.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Dig Deeper Seminars/Dig Deeper Seminars - Overview.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 Oct 2023 14:54:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite 2024 Main Talk 3 - The church is holy (Acts 4:32-5:11)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>Jesus' church really is for the whole world - but it is very different to the world. It is different in both radical generosity and radical holiness - being God's people, they begin to imitate God in both his grace and his seriousness about sin. <br>(NB The 14-18s will have thought about the Bible theme of holiness before this, but the 11-14s won't have as much of that background.) <br><br><a data-href="Bible Seminar 2 - The church is preaching and prayerful (Acts 4.1-31)" href="\unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-2-the-church-is-preaching-and-prayerful-(acts-4.1-31).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Bible Seminar 2 - The church is preaching and prayerful (Acts 4.1-31)</a><br><a data-href="Dig Deeper Seminar 2 - The radically-different church" href="\unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminar-2-the-radically-different-church.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dig Deeper Seminar 2 - The radically-different church</a><br><br><a data-href="Bible Seminar 3 - The church is organised and prioritised (Acts 6.1-7)" href="\unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-3-the-church-is-organised-and-prioritised-(acts-6.1-7).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Bible Seminar 3 - The church is organised and prioritised (Acts 6.1-7)</a>]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-3-the-church-is-holy-(acts-4.32-5.11).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Main talks/Main Talk 3 - The church is holy (Acts 4.32-5.11).md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 13:42:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite Main Talk 4 - The church is rejected (Acts 7:1-52)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>Stephen's speech shows that God's faithful people have always been the subject of persecution - but that God is present with his people wherever they are scattered to! We should expect that life will be hard, but that God will go with us.<br><br><a data-href="Bible Seminar 3 - The church is organised and prioritised (Acts 6.1-7)" href="\unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-3-the-church-is-organised-and-prioritised-(acts-6.1-7).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Bible Seminar 3 - The church is organised and prioritised (Acts 6.1-7)</a><br><a data-href="Dig Deeper Seminar 3 - The suffering-speaking church" href="\unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminar-3-the-suffering-speaking-church.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dig Deeper Seminar 3 - The suffering-speaking church</a><br><br><a data-href="Bible Seminar 4 - The church is for the nations (Acts 8.26-40)" href="\unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-4-the-church-is-for-the-nations-(acts-8.26-40).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Bible Seminar 4 - The church is for the nations (Acts 8.26-40)</a>]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-4-the-church-is-rejected-(acts-7.1-52).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Main talks/Main Talk 4 - The church is rejected (Acts 7.1-52).md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 13:59:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite Main Talk 5 - The church is for her enemies (Acts 9:1-31)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>Not only God-fearers like the Ethiopian eunuch, but even the fiercest enemy of the church can be forgiven and made a useful servant in Jesus' kingdom, as Paul is! Through Paul the gospel will go out to the nations - which, 2000 years later, includes us. So whoever you are, wherever you're from, and whatever you've done, Jesus offers you forgiveness and membership in his church!<br>(NB if anyone says that God gave Saul the new name Paul in this talk I shall sternly disapprove)<br><br><a data-href="Bible Seminar 4 - The church is for the nations (Acts 8.26-40)" href="\unite\unite-2024\bible-seminars\bible-seminar-4-the-church-is-for-the-nations-(acts-8.26-40).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Bible Seminar 4 - The church is for the nations (Acts 8.26-40)</a><br><a data-href="Dig Deeper Seminar 4 - The local-global church" href="\unite\unite-2024\dig-deeper-seminars\dig-deeper-seminar-4-the-local-global-church.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Dig Deeper Seminar 4 - The local-global church</a><br><br><a data-href="Main Talk 6 - The church is for you and for all" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-6-the-church-is-for-you-and-for-all.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 6 - The church is for you and for all</a>]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-5-the-church-is-for-her-enemies-(acts-9.1-31).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Main talks/Main Talk 5 - The church is for her enemies (Acts 9.1-31).md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 15:40:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unite Main Talk 6 - The church is for you and for all (Acts 13:32-40)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>The gospel of Jesus' resurrection means that everyone can be freed from sin and death - so don't scoff at that which can save you, put your trust in Jesus and get stuck in to his wonderful church on mission for him!<br><br><a data-href="Main Talk 5 - The church is for her enemies (Acts 9.1-31)" href="\unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-5-the-church-is-for-her-enemies-(acts-9.1-31).html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener">Main Talk 5 - The church is for her enemies (Acts 9.1-31)</a>]]></description><link>unite\unite-2024\main-talks\main-talk-6-the-church-is-for-you-and-for-all.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unite/Unite 2024/Main talks/Main Talk 6 - The church is for you and for all.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 15:40:38 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>